So good morning everyone my name is Muhammad Wiem Mkauer I'm an assistant professor at the
department of software engineering at Rochester Institute of Technology and today I'm going to
talk about refactoring: two challenges and two takeaways. So this all started when one of my
students came to me and said, Muhammad I noticed that whenever I am pushing a refactoring pull
request it typically takes longer for me to get it accepted, right. And for me that was a
bit confusing, because by definition refactoring is the art of improving the code software design and
cool source code without altering its behavior. So I would expect that to be something quicker
to be accepted by code reviewers. But since he mentioned this to me I said, why not, let's try
to see whether this is true or not, right. So what we have done is we have taken - at Xerox - we have
taken 171 pull requests that were purely about refactoring, we have identified all the developers
who did those pull requests - the authors of the pull requests - we also selected another set of 171
non-refactoring pull requests - either they're fixing a bugs or adding features -
and then we compare them in terms of how long it takes to make a decision, whether they get accepted
or rejected versus also how much discussion this triggers between the code authors and the
reviewers. And the results were interesting to us - they were challenging. So actually what we notice
is indeed, refactoring could - refactor or reviewing code - refactored code would take longer to be made
a decision of - they either accepted or rejected - and also it typically triggers a longer discussion
going back and forth between the code authors and the reviewers to be actually accepted or rejected.
And here this becomes a challenge for people to refactor their code and therefore we come
up with one recommendation. So this is the first challenge. The recommendation that we come up with
is, when you are submitting your refactoring pull requests keep in mind the three I's.
The first I is the intent, okay. The intent is answering the what - what exactly
are you doing with your refactoring, right, so you can be removing dead code or for
example removing or refactoring duplicate code right. And then also mention the how.
How are you refactoring your code, like, what are you doing? Are you renaming, are you extracting,
are you inling, are you moving, and explain exactly what are the code elements being involved
in your refactoring. And then of course you have to give the reviewers the way to assess
and evaluate your change by telling them exactly what you expect this refactoring to do, right. Is it
improving readability, reducing complexity, reducing coupling? Tell them exactly what this
is going to imply, and this is how they can also understand how to evaluate the intent through
the - through the why with the refactoring and then all the way to the implications.
Okay, so this is my first recommendation. When I used to live in France I used to cross this
railroad which says here "un train peut en cacher un autre" and which means, one train may hide another one, right, so this
problem that we noticed with your refactoring documentation may not necessarily be the only
problem we are facing when it comes to refactoring. Actually, many studies have been showing that
refactoring is getting misused and even underused. We talk about developers still refactoring things
manually. We talk about the lack of trust of anything that automatically refactor our code, and
as we can just we have just seen, we also have no formal documentation for refactoring, so are we
truly suffering from a lack of refactoring culture here okay? And in one of those studies they talked
about IntelliJ being one of the main IEs that developers use when they refactor their code, and
that's what triggers us to - RIT researchers to put - to join forces with JetBrains Research to
understand exactly how developers refactor their code using IntelliJ. And this is - was in a nutshell
our investigation is, we want to see how developers use IntelliJ to refactor their code. Okay, so what
we have done is, we went and we interviewed over a thousand developers. Many of them were, you know,
between three to over 16 years of experience with the development and we were asking them basically
this question: how do you refactor your code using IntelliJ, right? And also the results were again
showing another interesting challenge, right. So what we have found here is when the developers
typically rename code like they're renaming methods or classes, they actually use the IDE to do that. Maybe
this is because of that, you know, keyboard shortcut that makes things easier for you as developer to
rename things quickly, right. And this is good news because they are actually using the built-in
feature of IntelliJ which guarantees that your code would not introduce any regression when you
do this kind of changes, right. So this is a good - this is a good news. But on the other hand, when it
comes to extracting stuff, splitting a method into two for example, right, developers - half of
them actually use the IDE and the other half are still using the manual way of, maybe you know, copy
pasting, splitting manually, or creating a duplicate code then removing stuff here and there. So it's
not a perfect or healthy way of refactoring the code. And this may introduce errors in the code.
So this for us was a bit alarming. And even worse, when it comes to moving stuff,
you know, only one third of them, they are relying on the IDE to do that, right, and this becomes
really a problem for us to try to work on, right, so this is exactly what we have been finding and this
becomes the challenge, right. It is a challenge because we all are dealing with technical debt.
Okay, we had a whole workshop yesterday about technical debt and how we should manage it,
right, and obviously refactoring is one of the de facto tools to manage technical that we all have
been dealing with, we will be dealing with in the future of this piece of code that nobody has to
touch, right, and we should not - we should try to avoid even reaching that level, right, and this is
the challenge - technical debt is there, it will not never go away, and one way for us to start dealing
with this is to, next time when we open our IDE, we go to that menu "refactor", right, and let's get
familiar with it, and let's start learning how to use these features. Why? Because these features
can allow us to refactor our code in a more healthy way. If you want to know more details
about our study these are the references. With that being said, thank you very much.